sonoraquest.com 2012-06-22

# Privacy Policy < Sonora Quest Laboratories

By using our site, you consent to our privacy policies.

If changes to our privacy policies are made we will post those changes on this page and/or update the Privacy Policy modification date below.

**These policies were last modified in January 2011.**

Should you have any questions about our privacy policies, please contact us via email, call us at (602) 685-5000 or (800) 766-6721, or write to us at the following address:

Sonora Quest Laboratories/Laboratory Sciences of Arizona  
Attn: Enterprise Risk Management  
1255 West Washington Street  
Tempe, Arizona 85281

#### **Online Privacy Policy**

This online privacy policy applies only to information collected through our website and not to information collected offline. Please read our Notice of Privacy Practices to learn how medical information about you may be used and disclosed and how you can get access to this information.

#### **What information do we collect?**

We collect information from you when you register on our site, schedule Patient Service Center appointments, pay your bill online, subscribe to receive news and updates via email, respond to a survey, or fill out a contact form.

When using our site, as appropriate, you may be asked to enter your name, e-mail address, mailing address, phone number or credit card information. For some functions, you may visit our site anonymously.

Like most websites, we use cookies and/or web beacons to enhance your experience, gather general visitor information, and track visits to our website. Please refer to the 'do we use cookies?' section below for information about cookies and how we use them.

#### **What do we use your information for?**

Any of the information we collect from you may be used in one of the following ways:

  * To personalize your experience (your information helps us to better respond to your individual needs)
  * To improve our website (we continually strive to improve our website offerings based on the information and feedback we receive from you)
  * To improve customer service (your information helps us to more effectively respond to your customer service requests and support needs)
  * To process transactions (your information, whether public or private, will not be sold, exchanged, transferred, or given to any other company for any reason whatsoever, without your consent, other than for the express purpose of completing your transaction)
  * To send periodic emails (the email address you provide for Patient Service Center appointment scheduling, online bill-pay, or on a contact form, will only be used to send you information and updates pertaining to your request. If you decide to opt-in to our mailing list, you will receive emails that may include company news, updates, and related service information. Note: If at any time you would like to unsubscribe from receiving future emails, we include detailed unsubscribe instructions at the bottom of each email.)

#### **How do we protect your information?**

We implement a variety of security measures to maintain the safety of your personal information when you enter and/or access it on our site.

We offer the use of a secure server. All supplied sensitive/credit information is transmitted via Secure Socket Layer (SSL) technology and then encrypted into our Payment gateway providers database only to be accessible by those authorized with special access rights to such systems, and are required to keep the information confidential.

After a transaction, your private information (credit cards, social security numbers, financials, etc.) will not be stored on our servers.

#### **Do we use cookies?**

Yes. Cookies are small files that a site (or its service provider) transfers to your computers hard drive through your Web browser (if you allow) that enables the sites or service providers systems to recognize your browser and capture and remember certain information.

If you prefer, you can choose to have your computer warn you each time a cookie is being sent, or you can choose to turn off all cookies via your browser settings. Like most websites, if you turn your cookies off, some of our services may not function properly. However, you can still contact us by telephone to pay your bill or for general inquiries.

#### **Do we disclose any information to outside parties?**

We do not sell, trade, or otherwise transfer to outside parties your personally identifiable information. This does not include trusted third parties who assist us in operating our website, conducting our business, or servicing you, so long as those parties agree to keep this information confidential. We may also release your information when we believe release is appropriate to comply with the law, enforce our site policies, or protect ours or others rights, property, or safety. However, non-personally identifiable visitor information may be provided to other parties for marketing, advertising, or other uses.

Third party links: Occasionally, at our discretion, we may include or offer third party products or services on our website. These third party sites have separate and independent privacy policies. We therefore have no responsibility or liability for the content and activities of these linked sites. Nonetheless, we seek to protect the integrity of our site and welcome any feedback about these sites.

#### **Federal & State Online Privacy Compliance**

Because we value your privacy we have taken the necessary precautions to be in compliance with all applicable Federal and State privacy laws.

#### **Childrens Online Privacy Protection Act Compliance**

We are in compliance with the requirements of COPPA (Childrens Online Privacy Protection Act), we do not collect any information from anyone under 13 years of age. Our website, products and services are all directed to people who are at least 13 years old or older.

↑Top  

### **NOTICE OF PRIVACY PRACTICES**

Printer-friendly version

THIS NOTICE DESCRIBES HOW MEDICAL INFORMATION ABOUT YOU MAY BE USED AND DISCLOSED AND HOW YOU CAN GET ACCESS TO THIS INFORMATION. PLEASE REVIEW IT CAREFULLY.

Laboratory Sciences of Arizona and its subsidiary, Sonora Quest Laboratories, are committed to protecting the confidentiality of individuals’ laboratory test results and other protected health information (PHI) that we collect or create as part of our diagnostic testing activities.

We urge you to read this Notice of Privacy Practices carefully so that you will understand both our commitment to you and your privacy, and how you can participate in that commitment.

#### **About Our Laboratories’ Privacy Policy**

Our laboratory and its employees must obtain, maintain, use and disclose patient protected health information (PHI) in a manner that protects patient privacy and complies with all state and federal laws. We may only use or disclose the minimum amount of PHI necessary to perform a job or complete an activity.

We are required by law to provide patients with this Notice of Privacy Practices with respect to PHI, to maintain the privacy of PHI, to state the uses and disclosures of PHI that may be generated, and to list the rights of individuals and our legal duties with respect to their PHI. Your PHI includes medical information we obtain from your physician (such as name, address, date of birth, test ordered, etc.), health plan, or other sources, and the laboratory testing results that we create. An example of PHI is as follows: Jane Smith, Date of Birth: 2/15/68, resides at 123 Main Street, Anytown, AZ, cholesterol of 215 ng/ml.

We are required to abide by the terms of the Notice of Privacy Practices currently in effect and reserve the right to apply any changes to our policies and procedures to PHI created or received prior to the effective date of the Notice revision. The current Notice will be displayed on our website.

#### **How we obtain and maintain your Protected Health Information**

We obtain PHI from payers and, through the processing of testing orders, from physicians or other authorized persons who order laboratory tests. As a result of our testing activities, we create PHI -- laboratory results. We are required by law to maintain the PHI we collect and create for various reasons, including regulatory requirements, medical documentation, and laboratory certification and accreditation purposes. Whether your PHI is stored on paper, on a computer, or using other means, we will take reasonable care to maintain this information in a manner that will protect your privacy and confidentiality and the privacy and security of your PHI.

#### **How we protect the privacy of your Protected Health Information**

We protect the privacy of your PHI by training our employees and by requiring them to comply with company policies and procedures that allow access to and uses and disclosures of your PHI only for legitimate reasons. We verify the identity and check the authority of persons requesting PHI. We check that the appropriate information is provided to the requestor through a verification procedure, that is, by matching the information that the requestor must provide to us in advance with the information in our records. If the requestor cannot provide adequate information or the information provided does not match our records, we will not release your PHI. If the requestor is the patient, we will refer the requestor to his or her physician (or authorized person) to obtain the PHI. Our employees must comply with detailed policies and procedures regarding access to, and uses and disclosures of patients’ PHI. Our employees are required to use and disclose only the minimum amount of PHI needed for payment or other legitimate uses for our health care operations. Violation of these company policies or procedures is grounds for disciplinary action, up to and including termination of employment.

#### **How we use and disclose your Protected Health Information**

Your PHI will only be used or disclosed for treatment, payment, or healthcare operations purposes and other disclosures permitted or required by law, unless you send us written authorization permitting us to use or disclose your PHI for other purposes. You have the right to revoke your authorization at any time.

**For Treatment:** We may use your PHI or disclose your PHI to physicians and other authorized health care professionals who may need access to your PHI in order to treat you effectively. For example, in addition to your treating physician, we may provide a specialist consulting physician with information about your results to further validate the results before release to your physician.

**For Payment:** We may use your PHI or disclose your PHI to insurance companies, hospitals, physicians, health plans, or third parties to assist us in creating bills or claim forms for getting paid for our services. For example, we may send your name, date of service, test performed, diagnosis code, and other information to a health plan so that the plan will pay us for the services we provided.

**For Healthcare Operations:** We may use or disclose your PHI in the course of activities necessary to support our health care operations, such as performing quality checks on our testing, for teaching purposes, or for developing normal reference ranges for tests that we perform.

**Disclosures to Business Associates:** We may disclose your PHI to other companies or individuals who need your PHI in order to provide specific services to us. These other entities, known as “business associates,” must comply with strict contractual standards designed to ensure that they will maintain the privacy and security of the PHI we provide to them or which they create on our behalf. Our business associates must only use your PHI for designated treatment, payment, or health care operations purposes that we contract them to perform on our behalf. For example, we may disclose your PHI to the College of American Pathologists and other private accrediting organizations that inspect and certify the quality of our laboratories.

**As Permitted or Required by Law:** We may release your PHI for various public policy reasons that are authorized or required by law.

**Public Health:** We may disclose your PHI when reporting communicable disease results to public health departments as required by law.

**Health Oversight:** We may disclose your PHI in connection with governmental oversight, licensure, auditing, and other purposes. For example, governmental agencies periodically review our records to ensure that we are complying with the rules of various regulatory and licensing agencies. The U.S. Department of Health and Human Services and state Health Departments are examples of agencies that oversee aspects of our operations. Government agencies, such as OSHA or the FDA may require us to provide PHI in connection with an investigation or other proceeding.

**Law Enforcement:** We may also disclose PHI for law enforcement purposes. For example, we may be required to release PHI to identify or locate a suspect, fugitive, material witness, or missing person.

**Public Safety:** When the appropriate conditions apply, we may use or disclose PHI to prevent or lessen a serious and imminent threat to the health or safety of a person or the public.

**Specialized Government Functions:** We may disclose your PHI for military, national security, prisoner and government benefits (for health plans only) purposes.

**Other:** Here are other situations where, typically, the law permits or requires us to disclose  
your PHI:

  * Various state and federal laws permit or require disclosure of PHI. For example, workers compensation programs may require that we provide the results of laboratory testing as part of the case file.

  * Subpoenas, court orders, discovery requests or other legal process may require the disclosure of PHI in the context of a lawsuit or other legal proceeding.

  * In cases where state law is more restrictive than federal law, we are required to follow the more restrictive state law; for example, in the state of Arizona, we are not permitted to release laboratory test results directly to a patient.

#### **We may contact you for specific reasons**

Sometimes, we may want to contact you regarding health-related products or services that may be of interest to you, such as to direct or recommend alternative treatments, therapies, health care providers, or settings of care or to tell you about other health-related products or services offered by our organization. You have the right to opt out of programs that we offer. In other cases, we will contact you to obtain your authorization before using or disclosing your PHI for marketing purposes.

#### **Your rights concerning privacy and confidentiality**

**Access:** You or your authorized or designated personal representative has the right to inspect your PHI. We will deny access to certain information for specific reasons, for example, where state law prohibits such patient access.

**Amendments:** You have the right to request amendments to your PHI (but not to require us to make the requested amendments).

**Accounting:** You have the right to receive an accounting of disclosures of your PHI that were made by us for a period of up to six years prior to the date of your written request, but not including any disclosures made prior to April 14, 2003 when the Privacy Rule went into effect. This accounting does not include disclosures made for purposes of treatment, payment, health care operations, or certain other excluded purposes, but includes other types of disclosures, including disclosures for public health reporting or in response to a subpoena or court order.

**Restrictions:** You have the right to request that we agree to restrictions on certain uses and disclosures of your PHI, but we are not required to agree to your request request with the following exception. Effective for services provided to you after Feb. 16, 2010, you have the right to ask us to restrict the disclosure of PHI to your health plan for a service we provide to you where you have directly paid us (out of pocket, in full) for that service, in which case we are required to honor your request.

**Confidential Communications:** You have the right to request that we send your PHI to an alternate address.

**Notice of Privacy Practices:** You have the right to request a paper copy of this Notice.

**Complaints:** If you believe your privacy rights have been violated, you have the right to register a complaint with us or the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services. We will not retaliate against any individual for filing a complaint. You may file a complaint by calling us at (602) 685-5000 or (800) 766-6721, or by writing to us at the address located at the beginning of this Notice.

**How to exercise your rights:** Write to us with your specific written request and be sure to include sufficient information for us to identify all of your records. You may also contact us at the telephone number below to request an access form. We will consider your request and provide you a response within a reasonable timeframe. Should we deny your request, you have the right to ask for the denial to be reviewed by another healthcare professional designated by us. For additional details, or for instructions regarding how to exercise these rights, contact us, at: (602) 685-5000 or (800) 766-6721.

You may request a copy of this notice in paper form by contacting us at (602) 685-5000 or (800) 766-6721, or view an electronic, printer-friendly version of our Privacy Policy.

We reserve the right to amend this Notice of Privacy Practices, at any time, to reflect changes in our privacy practices and these changes will apply retroactively. Any such changes will be applicable to and effective for all Protected Health Information (PHI) that we maintain, including PHI we created or received prior to the effective date of the notice revision.

↑Top
